Guide to the George Ensle collection, 1973-2016 MS 680
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
George Ensle collection
1973-2017
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Ensle, George
MS 680
1.75 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
7.14 Gigabytes (Nearline access: MS0680aip_001 (7.14 GB))
19.9 Gigabytes (Nearline access: MS0680aip_002 (19.9 GB))
10.2 Gigabytes (Nearline access: MS0680aip_003 (10.2 GB))
14.3 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0680aip_004 (14.3 GB)
4.13 Gigabytes Nearline access: MS0680aip_005 (4.13 GB)
This collection consists of the fliers, news clippings, photographs, audio, and video chronicling the career of George Ensle.
Biographical / Historical
Growing up in Houston, George Ensle began taking guitar lessons at the age of 14. A few years later, his guitar teacher introduced him to Houston's folk club scene. He moved to Austin to attend the University of Texas in the fall of 1966. The following summer he began playing at Sand Mountain Coffee House where he befriended Townes Van Zandt, Guy Clark, Carolyn Hester, among others.
In the 1970s, he made Austin his permanent home. He toured the college circuit with Nanci Griffith. He also played in venues across the state of Texas, including Houston's Anderson Fair, the University of Houston Coffee House, and the Old Quarter. Towards the end of the decade, he began teaching music in economically disadvantaged schools as part of a Texas Commission for the Arts and the National Endowment for the Arts program.
Ensle released his first full length album in 1980 entitled, "Head On." He followed this up with "Heartwood" (1990), "One Gentle Hand: A Collection" (1999), "Live Set" (2006), "Build a Bridge" (2008), and "Small Town Sundown" (2012), and CD and DVD "Live from the Brauntex" (2013).
Ensle continues to play throughout Texas and runs the weekly Songwriters Showcase at Poodie's Roadhouse in Spicewood, TX.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains fliers, posters, news clippings, business records, audio and video. It is organized into four series.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by George Ensle in February 2017.
Accruals
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Folk music -- Texas -- Houston; Music
Document Types
Folk music; Folk-rock music
Subjects (Persons)
Ensle, George
- Series I: General files, 1973-2016
  - Album business, 1980-2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arts-in-School program, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards, 1978, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Business cards, 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business records, 1980s-2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Calendar, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1982-2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ephemera, 1991-2017 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fliers, 1970s-2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lyrics, 1970s-2010s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News clippings, 1973-2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Press releases, 1987-2007 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Promotion, 1970s-2010s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Set lists, 1970s-2010s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Small Town Sundown" companion book, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Songs For Blaze, A Friend of Ours", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Southwest Regional Folk Alliance, 2012-2014 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tour, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series II: Photographs, 1970s-2010s
  - Negatives, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1970s-2010s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proofs, 1970s-2010s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Audio and Video, 1980-2013
  - Test pressing (12" LP), ca. 1980 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: 5 tracks from the a side and 5 tracks from the b side.
  - "Head On," Gazebo Records (12" LP), 1980 (Box 2)
  - Live at Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant video, 1987-02-27
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mpg or mp4 and one access copy mp4.
  - The Rocket Bob Show; Citizens Live; Austin Outhouse video, 1987-04-15; 1988-05-06; 1980s
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mp4 and one access copy mp4.
  - Live at Anderson Fair Retail Restaurant video, 1987-05-08
  - Live performance, 1985-05-24
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mp4 and one access copy mp4. Songs include: "In Old-Fashion Love," "The Country Side of Town," "Bartalk," "Love Song," "Silver Spoons / Harvest Moon," "Devil's Mountain," "Old-Highway Cafe," "Talking By-Product Blues"
  - Live performance, 1987-08
    These born digital video files consist of one master copy mpg or mp4 and one access copy mp4. Songs include: "In Old-Fashion Love," "Cantas Con Tu Corazon," "The Country Side," "Hobo's Holiday," "Teenage Wind"
  - "Head On," Sawdust Records (12" LP), 1987 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "The Cadillac Cafe," "Love Song," "I Have to Drink to Drive This Thing," "Devil's Mountain," "Just and Alley Cat," "Steve's Song," "If It Comes Then It Comes," "Fishing Lines."
  - The Texas Connection - Rusty Weir, Michael Ballew, George Ensle video, 1990-05-02
  - The Texas Connection rough cut video, 1990-05-15
  - "Heartwood," (cassette tape), 1990 (Box 2)
  - "One Gentle Hand: A Collection" (CD), 1999 (Box 2)
  - "Live Set" (CD), 2006 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "Uncle Jack," "State of Grace," "The Troubadour Song for Townes," "Saving Me," "Circuit Preacher," "Blue Love," "Simple Pleasures," "Cantas Con Tu Corazon," "She Blooms Wherever She's Planted," "Coming Back Around."
  - Live Video (DVD), 2007-09-15 (Box 2)
  - "Build a Bridge" (CD), 2008 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "Walkin' Tall," "Everyday Heroes," "Bread of Life," "Second Chances," "Coming Back Around," "Christmas Truce of 1914," "Daybreak Snow," "Circuit Preacher," "Build a Bridge," "Sunsets."
  - "Small Town Sundown" (CD), 2012 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "Mom and Pop's," "Ballad of Cynthia Brown," "Grandma's Apron and Grandpa's Vest," "Faces in the Sun," "Billy Bob's Backyard," "Hill Country Moon," "Cowboy Church," "Small Town Sundown," "Hired Hands," "It's a Texas Thang," "Give Me Flowers While I'm Living," "April's Lullaby."
  - "Live from the Brauntex" (CD and DVD), 2013 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "Grandma's Apron and Grandpa's Vest," "Ballad of Cynthia Brown," "April's Lullaby," "It's a Texas Thang," "Texas Joke One," "All I Need," "Billy Bob's Backyard," "Eye of the Hurricane," "Coming Back Around," "Faces in the Sun," "Uncle Jack," "Texas Joke Two," "Uncle Jack," "Build a Bridge," "Small Town Sundown," "Martin's Song."
  - Songswarm, Vol. 1 (CD), 2017 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: George Ensle - "Knee Deep in a River"; Jack Saunders - "This Highway"; George Ensle - "Grandma's Apron and Grandpa's Vest"; Jack Saunders - "Moving On"
  - George Ensle video oral history, 2017-05-05
    These digitized video files consist of one master copy mp4 and one access copy located at scholarship.rice.edu.
  - "Retrospective", 2017 (Box 2)
    Contents include: Master wav and access mp3 of the following tracks: "If It Comes," "Fishing Lines," "Steve's Song," "Devil's Mountain," "Love Song," "Hobo's Holiday," "On the Sofa Outside," "The Old Highway Cafe," "Now and Then," "The Road," "Blue Tattoo," "Sunsets."
- Series IV: Oversized materials, 1975-2010s
  - Album business, 1985-1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Art, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fliers, 1970s-2010s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, 2000s (Box 3, Folder 4)